in this video we're going to be talking
about how you can actually use important
sampling a statistical method to be able
to decrease the variance of your monte
carlo options calculation so here we're
going to be talking about how you can
actually use the important sampling for
out of the money options specifically so
i want you to recall that for pricing
the european call option under risk
neutral pricing circumstances we use
this
risk neutral expectation of the
discounted payoff of the option and for
a call option here we've got our payoff
being st which under geometric brownian
motion dynamics is our initial stock
price times by the exponential to this
zt where zt is normally distributed with
this drift term and this variance term
now here we have the max between this
payoff so the difference between the end
of the st minus the strike and zero now
of course for this european call option
we have a closed form solution and that
is the black shoals formula that we have
here here we can calculate the black
shells formula for a
call or a put
now just seeing what that is we're going
to look at what that is for something
that's very far out of the money so here
we're going to consider a call with uh
initial price
a hundred
one year time to maturity and a strike
price of a over 170 so a very far out of
the money
strike with a discount rate of six
percent and a annualized volatility of
so here just calculating that black
shoals
price we get a price of 0.0789
so now
we're going to look at the benefits of
important sampling of course you don't
need to use important sampling for
something that has a closed form and a
solution but we're introducing important
sampling here as the benefit as you
increase your complexity for your monte
carlo simulation how you can actually
use important sampling and changing the
dynamics the
probability measure that you're actually
sampling from to actually get a greater
benefit and reduce the variance of your
calculation so now we're going to talk
about the benefits of important sampling
so here we've got the expectation of a
certain payoff function fx and then here
that's equivalent to the integral over
that payoff function
over that risk neutral pdf so that
probability measure
now in monte carlo what that means is
that we take the average of the
summation of all of that payoff
functions for all of those individual
simulated variables under that
probability measure so for a real world
example let's look at just how unlucky
25 standard deviation loss or return
would be now this is an example taken
from columbia university a fourth year
stats course so here for our monte carlo
simulation we've got theta which is our
estimate
and what we're trying to estimate is the
probability that x is greater than or
equal to 25 that's equivalent to
x is less than or equal to negative 25.
so this is equal to the expectation of
an indicator function where x is greater
than or equal to 25 where x is normally
distributed by the standard normal
distribution function so a mean of 0 and
a variance and standard deviation of 1.
so here we're going to use a million
variables in our monte carlo simulation
we're going to
have standard normally distributed
variables 1 million of them and we're
going to create this indicator function
where we count
if the z that we've simulated is above
25 then we count 1 if not it's 0 and
we're going to take the mean of that now
we calculate the standard error of this
and what we're trying to do is find the
95 confidence levels now do you think
with 1 million variables we are going
it's likely that we're going to sample
from a 25 standard deviation event
well definitely not because we know that
99.75 percent or thereabouts of the
information lies between -3 and 3.
so within three standard deviations are
we going to get a 25 standard deviation
is it likely no but how likely is it
well here we've had zero so we've got
zero so how can we actually calculate
that well we can use the method of
important sampling so we're going to
change the distribution that we're using
for our monte carlo simulation so here
we have the same distribution but now we
divide by a new distribution q and then
multiplied by q so we're actually going
to then in our monte carlo simulation
we're going to have this distribution f
and we're going to simulate variables
under our new distribution q
but then we're going to multiply this
summation by the ratio of the old
distribution divided by the new
distribution so let's see what that
looks like in in actuality so for our
case here for the normal distribution
and many other distributions we can work
out this analytical form of the
distribution of the pdf ratio between p
and q analytically so let's get that
form
here all we're doing is we've got our
indicator function and then our equation
for
the pdf of a normally distributed
function now this is the standard normal
distribution and all we need to do is
divide it by
the normal distribution with variance of
1 but of with mu just defined by mu
so here we then multiply by so we divide
by q when that's our ratio and we times
by q and when we submit all that
together then we get of this form here
so now let's use this formula in that
analytical ratio so now you'll notice i
don't have 1 million variables but i've
just got 1 000 and just trying to
demonstrate the power of important
sampling we're now going to choose a mu
25 which is much closer to where we're
trying to sample
so we have our new probability
density function
which is q which is centered around 25
with still a variance and standard
deviation of one and we have our
original probability distribution p
so we're sampling around our new
distribution we've got 1 000 variables
and then what we're going to do is we're
going to use numpy where which is our
indicator function again so where it's
greater than 25 we want 1 and then when
it's not it's zero so then we've got
multiplied by the ratio of the two pdfs
so p p pdf with that z random variable
and then divided by q
and then we get our z payoff now the
other way would have been directly using
that analytical ratio that we defined up
here so all i can do is take that
that numpy array where we've done the
where it said is greater than 25 take
one otherwise zero and then we multiply
that by the exponential of the term that
we derived up there then we can take the
mean
and then the standard deviation and
the standard error and even with only 1
000 variables we can see with a 95
confidence level
it lies between 2.18
and
4.24
times 10 to the negative
so that's such a small probability and
we've been able to estimate this very
efficiently with only a thousand
variables using important sampling so
let's think of this in terms of option
pricing now so option pricing here we're
going to talk about this ratio now
between our two distributions our old
one and our new one as the randon
nicodem derivative
so this comes from financial mathematics
and here we've got our risk mutual
expectation with a payoff of a given
stock price and we actually that is
equivalent to our new expectation under
a probability measure q0 i'm calling it
our new probability measure
with
the payoff of st
times by the random nicodem derivative
which is just the ratio between the old
probability distribution function under
this neutral measure and our new
risk neutral probability distribution
so we're going to conduct a simulation
under this new measure
q0 and then we're going to multiply by
the random nicodem derivative the ratio
of both probability functions with each
other and then we're going to be able to
calculate our option price more
accurately so let's talk about a far out
of the money put option to demonstrate
the empower of important sampling so
here we have that original expectation
that we showed before with our
discounted expectation of the payoff
under the risk neutral probability where
we have our dynamics of
the normal distribution with the drift
and the variance now we're actually
going to change the risk neutral
probability measure and we're going to
change the drift dynamics so that it's
centered around the strike
and when you do the math we get a normal
distribution of log k over s0
minus
sigma squared divided by 2 times by t
and now our drift term has changed but
our variance stays the same so now we
have a new probability risk measure of
which we're going to complete the
expectation under the same way that we
so this is almost the same to what we
just did before to count with a change
of measure we're changing the drift term
of this
expectation in our multi-color
simulation so we can actually calculate
efficiently
the price of the option so to actually
demonstrate the importance of that
change of measure what i'm going to show
you is just those two different
simulations so here in the monte carlo
this is what it would look like if we
were simulating under the wrist neutral
dynamics without change here we've only
got one price path out of 100 that has
actually crossed that 170 threshold
whereas if i change
the drift term so that it's centered
around
that strike at the end well then i get
something that i'm going to be able to
compute the expectation over even just a
small a handful of simulated simulated
variables so 100 in this monte carlo
simulation so that's what we're going to
do so we've just shown that you can
change the drift and you're going to get
a benefit now we've shown that visually
but now before we complete our
calculation we actually want to find the
optimum
drift to be using for a particular
option payoff now unfortunately there is
no general way in which we can find this
optimal distribution however we can find
the relatively optimal distribution
to reduce variance and that comes in the
formula here so here we want to minimize
the expectation
under the original probability density
function
so our risk neutral distribution of the
payoff squared times by that ratio
between our old and new distributions
and you'll see the new distribution
is actually indexed by mu so we're going
to use psi pi to then actually calculate
an optimal value for this mu so first
let's define our probability
distribution function so first we've got
our scipy stats norm so we've got our
new dt as our drift and our vol sdt as
our
diffusion term now for our q our new
distribution we've got this lambda
function with respect to mu and this is
the drift term that we're going to be
able to alter within our ratio
optimization
between these two distributions and then
we've got the same variance the same
vol s dt
now we've got this function which is z
t which is just going to be
taking in the variables x which are
going to be normally distributed
variables
which is our whiner process it's going
to have our drift and our
diffusion term and we're just going to
go
drift plus diffusion times by our wider
variable then we're going to have our
payoff function which we call in f0 and
this is going to be the discounted
payoff and the payoff again is just the
maximum of this value
final stock price so we've got a
function which is just s0 our original
stock price times by the exponential of
this value z which we're computing above
so we've got that
final stock price minus k so the maximum
of zero and then the call payoff
so now i'm going to for accuracy have
quite a few
simulated variables here i believe i've
got yes 1 million variables and here i'm
defining my
function that i want to minimize
so my function that i want to minimize
with respect to x now x is going to be
that drift
that we're looking for so the new
probability function i want a different
drift term that optimizes and minimizes
the variance of my payoff calculation so
here i've got my the mean the
expectation of that payoff discounted
payoff squared times by the ratio of the
two pdfs my original with the new one
and see here this is the only place that
i actually have my variable that i'm
trying to minimize in so it's the exact
same as this formula i've just codified
it here in a function so now we're going
to use scipy
optimize dot fmin so a minimization
function to be able to minimize this
function numerically now my estimate my
best guess is going to be
my good guess that i had before which is
let's just take
our drift term to b
centered around our strike so it's very
far out of the money let's center it
around the strike
so i've got our function that we're
trying to minimize i've got our best
guess and i just want to display what
the optimum is and here you can see that
i've got .61
now how how far was that away from our
original new dt well essentially you
know it was pretty close so our drift
term is actually a little bit higher
than uh then compared to centered around
k which is 0.5
which actually our optimum is 0.6 so
that's important to note so it's
actually a little bit more so we've got
more simulations that are actually
ending up
in the money and therefore we can
calculate that expectation more
accurately now let's compute the benefit
of actually calculating this option
price with different number of monte
carlo simulated variables so here i'm
going to change the number of simulated
variables from 100 all the way to 1000
now we're going to be
using the two methodologies one where we
just use our normal method which is the
risk neutral dynamics and one where we
use important sampling and then the
ratio between the two distributions with
our optimum
drift term obviously so optimum drift
term is this mu
now we take
a bunch of random variables and we
compute our distribution z we can then
calculate the final payoff the
discounted payoff
of all these sample variables and we're
going to multiply that through by our
ratio of our wrist neutral distribution
divided by our new distribution
and then we're going to take the
expectation we're going to take the mean
of all of these payoffs once we've done
that we can also calculate the standard
error
and we're going to store all of these
for our corresponding um
simulated variables 103 to 1000.
so the same thing applies here we're not
doing important sampling we're just
counting disk we're just using the
discounted expectation of a risk neutral
payoff where we have a normal drift and
uh volatility term so then we're also
going to calculate the standard error
reduction factor which we're just
defining as the standard error of the
without
important sampling divided by the
standard error of the monte carlo
simulation with important sampling so
now here i've created a pandas data
frame and here we're just going to look
at the difference between the prices and
the standard errors
so here just to remind you the black
shoals price is 0.0789
and i think the first thing to realize
is that the price without
important sampling at low simulated
variables we're getting nowhere near
that expected price so here at 100 we've
got zero which essentially means that
none of those paths or the risk neutral
distribution actually went out
above that strike price
so
what you can do is of course increase
the number of simulated variables but
that's very efficient in terms of
computation ability again i'll stress
here that when there is an analytical
solution for your option you don't need
to do this but again here i'm
demonstrating the power of importance
sampling when you come to tackle harder
problems that don't have analytical
solutions and you need to use
so for example anything path dependent
or stochastic volatility models that
you're trying to incorporate then you're
going to need to use this approach and
or possibly use this approach as a
variance reduction technique for out of
the money
options
so in comparison we can see that the
important sampling methodology straight
off the bat has got numbers very close
to this black shoals price even with
only 100 simulations so
let's compare them the standard error we
actually have a reduction in the
standard error of many multiples now
it's interesting to see here that you
know really undersells the power so here
the reduction in the standard error is
only six but look how far the price was
from an accurate price here we've
actually got using important sampling
0.078 which is nearly bang on and here
we've got the price without at .029
so oh it's only a multiple of 6 but the
pricing error is huge using without
important sampling
so as you go up we've we've nearly got a
number of factors that are above
multiple of 10. so hopefully we've
demonstrated what the power of actually
using important sampling is and how you
can go and apply that within your monte
carlo simulation now actually computing
this ratio can be quite difficult and
sometimes there is no analytical closed
form solution for it so instead you
actually have to use gersonov's theorem
within your monte carlo simulation to
calculate that and we're going to get
into that for more complex derivatives
in further videos
thank you very much for watching and if
you like this video please give it a
thumbs up and i will see you in the next
one